בוקר טוב *Boker tov* everybody, today's דף *daf* is מב *mem bet*,
42. We pick up with קתני מיהא katani miha *katani miha*.
So we are now dealing with the position of the debate of
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* and the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* where
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* says that the חכמים chachamim. *Chachamim*
say if you have something where all of the pieces are required
for a particular act to create פיגול pigul *pigul*, like four applications
of blood and so on, that you need to have a פיגול
pigul *pigul* thought at all four parts of it. Now that's only
components within a larger act. Like as opposed to if you have
פיגול pigul. *pigul* for just שחיטה shchita *shechita*, that's פיגול pigul. *pigul*.
פיגול pigul *pigul* for just הולכה *holacha*, for just זריקה zrikah *zerika*,
that's fine. Different that we all, that's fine. That makes פיגול pigul
*pigul*. Okay, but when it's different components of an act, of an
act that is normally called a מתיר matir. *matir* act, one of
the four key acts that is about the blood that makes the
קרבן korban. *korban* valid, then that's the question of מפגלין בחצי מתיר
mefaglin bechatzi matir. *mefaglin bechatzi matir* if a פיגול pigul *pigul* for
just one component of that act. By the way, component means a
discrete piece. So שחיטה shchita *shechita* of one of either the קנה
*kanei* or the esophagus, that's a חצי מתיר chatzi matir. *chatzi matir*.
Application of blood on one corner as opposed to all four, that's
a חצי מתיר chatzi matir, *chatzi matir*. חצי *chatzi* does not mean
exactly half obviously. But a פיגול pigul *pigul* thought partial, but a
פיגול pigul *pigul* thought on one step as you're walking it towards
the altar, that's not considered a חצי מתיר chatzi matir *chatzi matir*
because that is not a discrete component of this larger thing of
הולכה *holacha*. So anyway, so that's the question. So the simple sense
is because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says even if you
have a פיגול pigul *pigul* thought for just one of the applications
of blood, it is פיגול pigul? *pigul*, and the חכמים chachamim *Chachamim*
say עד שיפגל בכל המתיר *ad sheyifagel bechol hamatir*. You have to
have a פיגול pigul *pigul* thought in all of the components. Okay,
so the simple position of course of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi
Meir* is מפגלין בחצי מתיר mefaglin bechatzi matir. *mefaglin bechatzi matir*. No,
a פיגול pigul, *pigul* thought on one component suffices and that is
unquestionably the פשט pshat *pshat* of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
and so period. But in many of the sort of various ברייתות
baraitas *braitas* and whatever that we're going to quote. But we start
with the statement of I think it's רב פפא *Rav Pappa*, which
is who is it? Is it רב פפא *Rav Pappa*?
No, no, רבי Rebbe? שמעון בן לקיש *Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish*, excuse
me, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* who says that actually he
wants to re-read רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*. That even רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* requires פיגול pigul. בכל המתיר *pigul bechol
hamatir* and that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*'s position is only
when you had that thought at that one, a thought of one
part suffices when that one part is the first part. And therefore
it by default is assumed to be the thought for all the
other pieces. Okay, but again but as he says רש״י *Rashi* I
have no idea. רש״י *Rashi* says thought means speech by the way,
articulated thought. So that is how ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish*
interprets רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* and therefore we have a
problem though because all of the evidence is that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* thinks that even a פיגול pigul *pigul* thought in
a middle component makes פיגול pigul *pigul* and this is forcing, gonna
force ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* to do somersaults to re-interpret
these texts. Okay, so let's actually, you know what, let's pick up
from the last line of מא עמוד ב *mem aleph amud bet*
just to sort of get that started again. Two lines from the
bottom מא עמוד ב *mem aleph amud bet*, מיתיבי *Meisvei*. במה דברים
אמורים be-meh devarim amurim בדמים הניתנים על מזבח mizbeach, החיצון *Bameh devarim
amurim bedamim hanitnim al mizbe'ach hachitzon*, when is it true that a
פיגול pigul *pigul* for the first one application of blood, well specifically
the first application of blood makes פיגול pigul. *pigul*? That's when you're
talking about the outer altar and therefore the first application is ends,
you know you're supposed to do the rest but the animal the
קרבן korban. *korban* is valid after the first. So after the first
it's no longer considered part of the מתיר matir. *matir*. אבל aval
דמים הניתנים על מזבח mizbeach. הפנימי *Aval damim hanitnim al mizbe'ach hapnimi*,
but if it's about the inner altar, כגון ארבעים ושלוש שביום הכיפורים
*kagon arbaim veshalosh shebeyom hakippurim* the 43 applications of blood on יום
הכיפורים *Yom Kippur* which we sort of figured out here. We should
repeat it because it's going to come up a little bit later.
So you have seven and one on the כפורת kaporet, *kaporet*, seven
and one on the פרוכת parochet. *parochet*, that you know or one
and seven I should say, אחת אחת ואחת *achat achat ve'achat* etc.
So that's 16 and then you do that separately for the פר
par והשעיר *par ve'hasair* that's 32. Then you mix the blood together
and you do seven on the top המזבח *hamizbe'ach* and four to
the corners. Actually you do the reverse the order, excuse me, you
don't reverse the order, I wrote the order wrong, okay, four on
the corners and seven on the top, that's another 11 that gets
you 43. Okay so the 43 applications of blood ואחד עשר של
פר כהן kohen המשיח *ve'achad asar shepar kohen hamashiach* and the 11,
the four and the seven, the seven on the curtain, not seven
plus one, of the פר *par* of the כהן גדול kohen gadol.
*kohen gadol*, ואחד עשר של פר העלם דבר של ציבור *ve'achad asar
shepar helam davar shel tzibbur* and the 11 of the פר *par*
for when בית דין *beis din* rules incorrectly, in these cases פיגל
בין בראשונה בין בשניה בין בשלישית bein berishona bein bishniya bein bishlishis,
*pigel bein berishona bein beshniya bein beshlishis*, so if the פיגול pigul.
*pigul* thought was on any one of those, so רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* for the first, second, third set or first, second,
third application, רבי מאיר אומר פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת Rebbi Meir omer
pigul vechayavin alav kares. *Rabbi Meir omer pigul vechayavin alav kareis*. That's
enough to make פיגול pigul *pigul*. מפגלין בחצי מתיר mifaglin bachatzi matir,
*mefaglin bechatzi matir*. וחכמים אומרים אין בו כרת kares. עד שיפגל בכל
המתיר *Vachachamim omrim ein bo kareis ad sheyifagel bechol hamatir*. It has
to be by everything. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* is
stricter by this I should say than even by the outer חטאת
chatat *chatas*, because the outer חטאת *chatas* if you had a פיגול
pigul *pigul* thought by any application after number one, then it's not
פיגול pigul *pigul*. Here רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says no
since they're all required, any פיגול pigul? *pigul* thought on any one
of the 11 or the 43. Okay. The חכמים chachamim *Chachamim* are
more lenient than a חטאת *chatas*, than the outer חטאת *chatas*. For
the outer חטאת *chatas* פיגול pigul. *pigul* for the first makes it
פיגול pigul, *pigul*. Here... There the חכמים chachamim need the פיגול pigul
thought for everything. Okay, so just to appreciate the contrast. But anyway,
רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir it's pretty clear, says מפגלין בחצי מתיר. mifaglin
bachatzi matir. It doesn't have to be the first one like ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish. wants to re-read רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir right? Even
one that is some, that is in the middle. So that's a
pretty darn good proof that ריש לקיש Resh Lakish, is incorrect. So
the גמרא Gemara says: תני מיהא, Tani miha, we teach nevertheless, פיגול
בין בראשון בין בשני בין בשלישי ופליג, pigul bein barishon bein bashaini
bein bashlishi upalig, that we're talking about a פיגול pigul. thought in
any of the middle sets or any of the subsequent applications of
blood and רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir still says it's פיגול. pigul I
love the פליג palig and פיגול. pigul Okay, אמר רבי יצחק בר
אבין: amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avin: הכא
במאי עסקינן כשפיגל בשחיטה דחד מתיר הוא, hacha bemai askinan k'shepigel bishchita
dechad matir hu, בשחיטה. bishchita. So there's a little debate, רש"י Rashi
tells us and תוספות Tosfos concedes רש"י's Rashi read is the best.
רש"י Rashi basically says what it means here is, is that you
sp-,
a classic discussion in מסכת יומא Masechet Yoma is what happens when
you spill the blood in the middle of the process, do you
have to start all over again from the beginning or can you
pick up where you left off and so on? Because what you're
going to have to do now is get another cow or another
goat, שחט shacht it again, get more blood, so do you have
to start from the beginning or can you start where you left
off? Okay, and there's different places of where you left off. Like
let's say you finished doing the stuff of the, you know, of
the inner מזבח, mizbeach, so then maybe I can pick up for
the, I mean, you know, the inner, the ארון, Aron, the כפורת,
kaporet maybe I can pick up then when it comes to the
outer altar, you know, when it comes to the altar or the
פרוכת. parochet, But let's say within the seven of the כפורת kaporet
I spilled. Well, if you spill within a set, then, you know,
within even one, one, you know, one very tight set, then maybe
you have to start again from the beginning. Anyway, that's the issue.
So רש"י Rashi says
what we're talking about here is that you, let's say you spilled
the blood between, you know, the כפורת kaporet, and the פרוכת, parochet
okay? So now you have to שחט shacht another animal and get
more blood. Okay, so this is, when we say you had a
פיגול pigul? thought whether it's the first or the second or the
third, let's say first, second, and third means first, second, or third
set, it doesn't mean you're just sprinkling blood straight and somewhere here
in the second set you had a פיגול pigul thought. That would
be חצי מתיר. chatzi matir, And again, ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish claim
is that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir does not say מפגלין בחצי מתיר.
mefaglin be-chatzi matir. No, what happened was you had a פיגול pigul.
thought on the second set because you spilled the blood, you did
another שחיטה shchita of a cow right here, okay, and because you
did another שחיטה shchita of a cow right here, so it was
for the שחיטה shchita. of the second set. In the bizarre case,
in the unlikely case that you spilled it. And since your pi-,
or you spilled the cow between the פרוכת parochet and the and
the and the inner מזבח. mizbe'ach. So you did another שחיטה shchita
here and you had a פיגול pigul thought related to the third
set because you're now, because you're doing a שחיטה. shchita So in
that case where you have to introduce a שחיטה shchita, because it
got spilled, that was a פיגול pigul, thought that was on a
full act, okay? And that's
why, so that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. Again, that is a
very דחוק dachuk read, but that is the way to continue to
insist that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. says you need to be מפגל
בכל המתיר. mefagel bechol hamatir. Okay, so that's the answer. So let's,
but the גמרא's Gemara not happy. So the גמרא Gemara says: הכא
במאי עסקינן כשפיגל בשחיטה דחד מתיר הוא, hacha bemai askinan k'shepigel bishchita
dechad matir hu, it's one מתיר. matir Okay, the שחיטה shchita is
the מתיר. matir Okay, אי הכי, ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara,
מאי טעמא דרבנן? mai taama deRabbanan? Okay, but in that scenario that
you had a פיגול pigul thought during שחיטה, shchita okay, it's true
it was a second שחיטה shchita that needed to be done in
the middle, but שחיטה shchita is always defined as a full concrete
as a full act. So why would the רבנן Rabbanan say that
it's not פיגול? pigul, אמר רבא: amar Rava: מאן חכמים? man Chachamim?
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Okay, within this read that it's a שחיטה
shchita? act in the middle, I will tell you that the חכמים
chachamim, that say that would not be enough is רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer because it's by the, because we've now created a very bizarre
scenario, right? We've now created a case where normally how many שחיטות
shchitas do you need? One, right? Now we've created a scenario where
you need two שחיטות shchitas in order to get the requisite blood,
not two different קרבנות, korbanot, two שחיטות shchitas essentially for the same
קרבן. korban Okay, so and you know, so is the second שחיטה
shchita a full מתיר matir or is it partial מתיר matir because
it's somehow now working together with the other שחיטה? shchita Or it's
a partial מתיר matir. because it's somehow necessary to continue the process
of the blood, but it wasn't the initial שחיטה shchita. of the
קרבן. korban Okay? So actually you could see an interesting reason why
the רבנן Rabbanan might disagree and why they might say that, you
know, that even though this is a full שחיטה shechitah act, we
don't consider this enough to create פיגול pigul because it's a second
שחיטה. shechitah. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is now going to
explore, a way to say that, and it says it by comparing
this to a position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Now רבי אליעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer position was, is not about פיגול, pigul, it's about, it's
about שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, or you know, העלאת חוץ, ha'alas chutz,
bringing things outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but we're going to
make the analogy. Okay, so let's take a look. מאן חכמים? man
Chachamim? רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דתניא דתנן detanya detnan מתניתין: matnitin: הקומץ
והלבונה והקטורת ומנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח ומנחת נסכים,
hakometz vehalevona vehaktoret uminchat kohanim uminchat
kohen mashiach uminchat nesachim,
these are all things that are... fully burnt on the מזבח mizbe'ach
*mizbeach*. הקומץ Hakomets, *Hakometz* the handbreadth from the מנחה minchah. *mincha*, הלבונה
*halevonah* the frankincense from the מנחה mincha. *mincha*, קטורת ketores *ketores* the
frankincense that's burned on the on the inner altar, מנחת כהנים minchas
kohanim ומנחת כהן kohen, משיח *Minchas kohanim u-minchas kohen mashiach*, whether it's
a סתם stam, *stam* מנחה mincha, *mincha* that a כהן *kohen* brings,
or whether it's the regular מנחה mincha *mincha* that the כהן גדול
*kohen gadol* is required to bring, those are all goes the full
מנחות *minchos* goes on the altar, okay. ומנחת נסכים nesachim, *U-minchas
nesachim* and a מנחה mincha *mincha* that comes with the wine and
the oil or whatever that comes with the קרבן korban *korban*. שהקריב
*She-hikriv* now, so all these things would totally be burnt on the
altar. So the principle is if you שחט shacht *shacht* outside the
בית המקדש Beit Ha-mikdash *Beis Hamikdash* or burn stuff on an altar
outside of the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, you're חייב chayav *chayav* for
שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz *shchutei chutz* or העלאת חוץ halaat chutz, *hala'as
chutz*. So it says in all those cases שהקריב מאחת מהן בחוץ
כזית kezayit בחוץ חייב chayav *she-hikriv me-achas mei-hen be-chutz kezayis be-chutz chayav*.
You're חייב chayav *chayav*, okay fine. That's a straight הלכה halachah *halacha*
about הקרבת חוץ chutz, *hakravas chutz*. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer פוטר *Rabbi
Eliezer potar*, Rabbi Eliezer exempts עד שיקריב את כולן *ad she-yakriv es
kullan*. כולן
*Kullan* here does not mean that you have to do the קומץ
komets *kometz* and the לבונה levonah *levonah* and the קטורת ketores *ketores*
and the מנחת כהנים *minchas kohanim*. It means the entirety of any
one of them. Okay, a כזית kezayit, *kezayis* is not enough. Okay,
now why? Because he would say look, I understand that a כזית
kezayit. *kezayis* is normally a minimum שיעור *shiur*. And the way רש''י
Rashi *Rashi* explains just to help clarify for you is if you
took this מנחה *mincha*, this or this קומץ komets, *kometz*, let's take
the example of just a קומץ komets, *kometz*, you took this קומץ
komets *kometz* and you were already מקריב *makriv* some of it on
the inner on the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbeach* in the בית המקדש *Beis
Hamikdash* and then you took the rest and you took a כזית
kezayit *kezayis* of the rest and you burned it outside, okay then
that you would be חייב chayav. *chayav*. Because I agree that the
amount that you're חייב chayav, *chayav* is a כזית kezayit *kezayis* when
you bring it outside. But the thing has to be considered to
be like a meaningful הקרבה *hakrava*. So if some of this was
already brought on the in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* and then
this whole thing by the fact that part of it was put
on the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* is already sort of considered to
be like
partial part of an act of הקרבה *hakrava*, then even a כזית
kezayit *kezayis* outside is enough. But if you go outside and you
never brought any of this and you just put a כזית kezayit
*kezayis* outside, so since normally it's the full amount that goes on
the מזבח mizbeach *mizbeach*, right? So a כזית kezayit *kezayis* outside is
not a sufficiently meaningful act when you're not doing the full amount
that goes to the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbeach*. Maybe a better way to
say this or
whatever is you're only חייב chayav. *chayav* outside in something that you
would bring inside. Now normally that's defined, like what if
he slaughtered outside and did the rest inside?
Well, I don't know, that's a good question. But let's not get
there. Okay, so that's normally sort of determined like to say what
types of things, like I don't know if it has a בעל
מום *baal mum* or it's this or that, only a type of
thing that you would bring inside. But it is making this parallel
that the outside bringing has to be
somehow seen as comparable to the inside bringing. So therefore since the
inside what has to go on the מזבח mizbeach? *mizbeach* is the
entirety, he says on the outside you're not חייב chayav, *chayav* until
it's the entirety. If you have a way to connect it to
the inside bringing in a more concrete way by having put already
some of it on the altar, a כזית kezayit *kezayis* would be
enough. But if it's not if it's not connected that way, you
need it to be seen as a full act that would have
been done inside, it has to be the full קומץ komets *kometz*
or the full amount of לבונה levonah *levonah* or whatever the case
might be. Okay, that's all very nice and interesting if we were
learning about הקרבת חוץ chutz *hakravas chutz*. What does that have to
do with us? What?
I'm sure we will soon.
Yeah, we will soon. Okay, there's some of things that we're always
learning about. פיגול pigul *Pigul*, שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz, *shchutei chutz*, like
these are things that get interwoven in almost every discussion, which is
a fascinating point. Anyway, so how is this relevant? So תוספות Tosafot,
*Tosafos* says it's relevant in the following way. I'm going to use
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*'s explanation, it's a little clearer than רש''י Rashi. *Rashi*.
תוספות Tosafot: *Tosafos* says it's relevant in the following way. The standards
of פיגול pigul. *pigul* are usually higher than the standard to be
meaning in order to be פיגול pigul *pigul* than are the standards
of שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz *shchutei chutz*. Okay, how do I know
this? Because
he says like this: let by
פיגול pigul, *pigul*, right? Let's say according to the רבנן *Rabbanan* of
מפגלין אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר Ein mefaglin be-chatzi matir, *mefaglin ein mefaglin
be-chatzi matir*. If I had a פיגול pigul *pigul* thought about just
the קומץ komets. *kometz*, have I created פיגול pigul. *pigul*? No, because
I also the לבונה levonah *levonah*, the frankincense, those are the two
מתירין matirin. *matirin* of a מנחה *mincha*, right? Both the handbreadth and
the frankincense. So even a פיגול pigul. *pigul* thought of the whole
קומץ komets *kometz* isn't פיגול pigul. *pigul* until I also do the
לבונה levonah *levonah*. When we come to שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz *shchutei
chutz*, right? I am חייב chayav. *chayav* for offering up just a
כזית kzayit *kezayis* of the מנחה *mincha*. You got me? So what
you need a פיגול pigul *pigul* thought for, focusing on the רבנן
*Rabbanan* of אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר ein mepaglin b'chatzi matir, *ein mefaglin
be-chatzi matir* and presumably we're saying now רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi
Meir* holds the same thing, okay. Anyway, a פיגול pigul. *pigul* thought
is only פיגול pigul. *pigul* if it's on like the entirety of
a מתיר matir *matir*. Whereas for the rabbis who disagree with רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*, בחוץ *be-chutz* you're חייב chayav *chayav* even
on a כזית kzayit *kezayis*. So we can infer from this, assuming
everybody agrees to this structure, we can assume from. from this, that
if you are פטור patur outside for חוץ, chutz. you're definitely פטור
patur for פיגול. pigul. פיגול pigul. you require a lot more to
make פיגול pigul than to be חייב chayav, outside. Clear? Okay. So,
therefore, if now Rabbi Eliezer is saying that you are, you are
פטור patur for a, a כזית kzayit until it's the full amount,
certainly he would say you'd be פטור patur for פיגול pigul in
the a comparable type of a case, given this קל וחומר. kal
va-chomer. Okay, fine, but we're not talking about a כזית, kezayit we're
talking about doing a שחיטה shechitah between these various things. Okay, so
this is where the comparison gets a little tricky and I'm not,
I don't have a good way of explaining it, but somehow the
assumption is, now there's the, the next analogy is, is that the
קומץ komets, outside is similar to the שחיטה. shechitah And you could
sort of see that why? Because קומץ, kometz I'm not a קומץ,
kometz a כזית. A כזית is like a discrete act, it's an
act that you could be חייב chayav for for שחוטי חוץ shechutei
chutz under the right circumstances. A כזית is a discrete act, but
it's a discrete act that somehow is not the totality. So, it,
you know, we're somehow comparing it to doing a שחיטה shechitah here,
which is a discrete act of שחיטה shechitah to get you the
blood, but ultimately it's part of a second שחיטה shechitah and it's
part of whatever, etc., etc. Now, it still seems like the comparison
is weak, right?
A כזית of the קומץ kometz is like a חצי מתיר, matir?
right? So, okay, fine, so that you're פטור patur for for פיגול.
pigul We're trying to create a scenario where you have a full
מתיר matir but it's somehow coming in the middle. So, it's very
strange and again, trust me, רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafos you know,
they, they're not, they don't fully explain it, what the comparison is.
The גמרא Gemara is going to drop it. Okay, but there's some
rough analogy here that because we see Rabbi Eliezer has a, you
know, you know, is,
exempts you for חוץ chutz by less than a full amount, okay,
even though it's somehow meaningful, that's going to be able to explain
the חכמים. chachamim, Now that we've created this weird case that we're
talking about a שחיטה shechitah that occurred in the middle, that could
explain why the חכמים chachamim. would say that's not פיגול. pigul All
right, I don't know, I'm very confused, I don't know about you.
But what I will say is, is that with dropping Rabbi Eliezer,
that just makes it all these analogies, okay, it's, you could understand
an interesting debate. אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר, matir. but שחיטה shechitah normally
is a whole מתיר. matir. What happens when שחיטה shechitah occurs in
the middle and in the middle of the מתיר matir, process of
blood and it's coming to get you the more blood that you
need? Is the שחיטה shechitah a חצי מתיר matir. or is the
שחיטה shechitah a whole מתיר? matir. So, forget Rabbi Eliezer. That would
have actually been an interesting debate in that scenario whether we look
at שחיטה shechita as a whole מתיר matir, or a partial מתיר.
matir, But comparing it to Rabbi Eliezer is very strange. Yes, Michael?
Just so I understand, did you say that according to חכמים Chachamim,
like when you have your standard you need both the קומץ kometz
and the לבונה levonah to have פיגול pigul. thoughts?
Yeah. So, and you said פיגול pigul. is harder than שחוטי חוץ,
shchutei chutz right?
Meaning שחוטי חוץ chutz you're definitely חייב chayav if you do the
whole קומץ. kometz Right, even if you don't need the קומץ kometz
and even if you do a כזית of
it, because we were just
saying, and even if you just do a כזית of the קומץ,
kometz right.
Because by, by שחוטי חוץ the הלכה halachah? is not כל המתיר,
kol ha-matir, okay? It's not about a מתיר. matir, It's about a
certain type of an act of עבודה avodah that gets done and
so on, it's a just a completely different structure.
Yeah, by שחוטי חוץ there's a lot to חוץ.
And it includes העלאה, ha'ala'ah, right. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay, so anyway somehow we're trying to explain in
this interesting case of שחיטה shechitah? between the two acts, what would
the debate be? And we're trying to link the חכמים Chachamim that
would say that you are, that you are פטור to this Rabbi
Eliezer.
That's correct, right, for our הלכה?
halacha Yeah. So, the גמרא Gemara says והא אמר רבא, ve-ha amar
Rava, but wait a minute, you can't say that this is a
Rabbi Eliezer approach just because Rabbi Eliezer is more, you know, exempts
you more by the כזית of the חוץ outside. Why? Because רבא
Rava says ומודי רבי אליעזר בדמים, u-modeh Rabbi Eliezer be-damim, Rabbi Eliezer
would agree when it comes to blood that you are not, that
you don't need to do all the amount of blood outside the,
outside the בית המקדש to be
חייב. chayav דתנן, de-tnan, we turn a משנה, Mishnah,
רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים, Rabbi Eliezer ve-Rabbi Shimon omrim, ממקום שפסק
משם הוא מתחיל. mi-makom she-pasak misham hu matchil. Now,
okay, now
we actually are going to make yet a third analogy. All the
different analogies get, get very, very complicated and strange. Okay, so there's
a debate of Rabbi Eliezer and of the חכמים, Chachamim. Rabbi Eliezer,
Rabbi Shimon, which is exactly this. If you spill it in the
middle, wait, let me just quickly check רש"י. Rashi
Right, so this, this is the debate I was telling you before,
which is you spill the blood somewhere here in the middle, okay,
of the process. Do you have to start all over again or
can you שחט shacht a new animal and pick up where you
left off? Okay, so Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Shimon are saying that
ממקום שפסק משם הוא מתחיל, mi-makom she-pasak misham hu matchil, that if
you spill the blood, get, שחט shecht another animal, pick up where
you left off. Okay, how is that relevant? So somehow it's like
relevant in the following way. Since we see that רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says that every application of blood that you do inside basically
accomplishes something because you're not going to have to redo it, okay,
so it's not like it requires everything else to somehow be meaningful.
You're not done, but what's... the part that was done is done.
Okay, so since he says that every application of blood inside sort
of, you know, you don't have to go back and redo it,
by itself it sort of allows you to move on even if
you spilled it, okay, so once רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that,
we're going to somehow infer that if you did just a little
bit of blood outside, you didn't do all the applications, since there's
some meaning to a little bit of blood inside, even though it's
not the whole מתיר, matir, then therefore you're חייב, chayav there's no
meaning for just a כזית of the קומץ kometz inside. If I
did a כזית of the קומץ komets on the altar, I was
did not accomplish anything. Okay, of course you could say just do
the rest, so you sort of did, but okay, let's bracket that,
whereas if I did a little bit of blood inside, okay, the
קרבן korban is still not valid, but if it gets spilled, you
don't have to do a redo. Okay, so that means it did
accomplish something. So therefore based on that, we're going to say that
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say if you do just a little
bit of blood outside you're חייב. chayav Even if you do a
little bit of the hand-breath outside you're not חייב, chayav if you
do a little bit of blood outside you are חייב. chayav You
sort of with me here? Okay, so by שחוטי חוץ or העלאת
חוץ, that makes sense. Fine. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you
need something to have more weight to be חייב chayav outside than
a little bit, blood, a little bit of blood has more weight
than a little bit of whatever, and therefore that's the difference. What
the heck does that have to do with this scenario of whether
שחט shecht the cow here makes פיגול pigul or doesn't make פיגול?
pigul So what תוספות says is, it really doesn't have that much
to do with it. But what it does is it complicates the
picture. It basically says, this is how I read תוספות: Don't try
to infer from רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position about חוץ what he
would say by פיגול. pigul Oh, look, if רבי אליעזר says that
this little, you know, that this little כזית of קומץ you're not
חייב, chayav somehow that'll tell us that שחט shecht the cow here
won't make פיגול, pigul whatever that comparison was. He says the picture
is more complicated than that, because while he says you're not חייב
chayav for a little piece of the of the hand-breath, he does
say you're חייב chayav for a little bit of blood. So you
don't... so רבי אליעזר's position outside is like complicated exactly what a
little bit you're חייב chayav for and a little bit you're not
חייב chayav for, okay? And therefore there's really no way of drawing
some straight line from what he says about outside to telling me
whether he would say when you שחט for a cow that comes
in between these two stages, whether that's going to be פיגול pigul
or not פיגול. pigul Okay, so that whole thing was very complicated,
we didn't really understand what type of analogy the גמרא Gemara was
drawing anyway, but anyway it's going to get it to reject this
very difficult read of the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
the חכמים, Chachamim although, it is a fascinating question. If
אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר, matir, what is the story about a whole
שחיטה shechitah, that's coming in the middle to allow you to continue
the blood? But okay, moving on. Anyway that clearly is not what's
going on in this תוספתא Tosefta here in this debate of רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים. Chachamim So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay,
ואמר רבא, v'amar Rava, כגון שפיגל בראשונה ושתק בשניה וחזר ופיגל בשלישית.
kegon shepigeil barishona v'shataki bishniya v'chazar v'pigeil bishlishit. Okay, you're right. According
to
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir פיגול pigul, would really only works on the
first act, because then it defines the rest. Again, this is according
to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish So what does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
mean when he says if you have פיגול pigul. on the first,
second, or third, it's פיגול? pigul What he doesn't mean is first,
second, and third, first, second, or third. What he means is, and
again, try to read this into the words, he means if you
have פיגול pigul on the first, and then also on the second
and the third, then it's פיגול. pigul So the answer is like,
okay, that's sort of obvious, since פיגול pigul on the first itself
is פיגול, pigul, of course פיגול pigul, on another one or two
would be פיגול, pigul, right? Everybody with me here? We're reading רבי
מאיר to not say פיגול pigul on any one makes פיגול, pigul
to make it work with ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish. we're saying according
to רבי מאיר, פיגול pigul on one and also on some of
the others makes פיגול. pigul But isn't that obvious? If פיגול pigul
on just one makes פיגול, pigul then פיגול pigul on one and
three makes פיגול. pigul Why would we be giving that case? So
the גמרא Gemara says, no, here's why we're giving that case. מהו
דתימא, mahu detayma, I might have thought, אי סלקא דעתך דאש ראשונו
הוא עושה, ee salka datach dash rishono hu ose, if really everything
is defined by the first act and that's what allows us to
say you're חייב for רבי מאיר when you did it on the
first act. So מהדר פיגולי בשלישית למה לי? mehadar pigulei bishlishis lama
li? So you know there's a principle is like כל המוסיף גורע,
kol hamosif gore'a, right? If you're adding then it raises questions then
it in a way it undermines. Okay. If you had just done
it on the first one, it would have defined for רבי מאיר
the whole process as פיגול. pigul But if you did it on
the first and the third and not the second, then that's... then
maybe that because you're insisting on defining each act, you weren't allowing
the first to define the process. You also had a statement at
the third to make it פיגול. pigul So that actually now may
problematize the second and maybe will tell us that the second that
it's דווקא davka not פיגול pigul during the second. At least that
I could have thought that. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that
no, that that also is פיגול. pigul Okay, so now it's not
as bad as the read before. But the rather than reading it
again, rather than as opposed to the פשט pshat of רבי מאיר
that מפגלין בחצי מתיר, matir? either one or two or three is
fine. Now what we're reading it is one is one make... not
fine, but makes פיגול. pigul, Now we're reading it: one makes פיגול.
pigul, Oh, and by the way, if you did one and one
of the other ones, guess what? That's also פיגול. pigul, Okay? And
that's what we mean to be mentioning the other ones. Okay, so
מתקיף לה רב אשי, maskif lah Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi
asked מידי שסקה קתני? midi shaska katani? What? That you can't read
that into the משנה. Mishna. משנה Mishna didn't say he did one
and then he didn't do two and then he did three. It
says: "one or two or three." Okay. אלא אמר רב אשי, ela
amar Rav Ashi, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bamay askinan, what are we
talking about? כגון שפיגל בראשונה ובשניה ובשלישית. kegon shepigel berishona uvishniya uvishlishis.
So this... so this is also problematic because it says בין בראשונה
בין בשניה בין בשלישית, whether one or whether two or whether three.
But he's reading it is: you had פיגול pigul. on one and
on two and on three. Okay. And it's going to be a
similar type of a point. For רבי מאיר you're חייב if it's
one alone. It's פיגול pigul if it's one alone. Okay? And guess
what? It's also a פיגול pigul if it's one, two, and three,
and not four. Okay? And that's how we're reading the ברייתא. Baraisa.
Not one or two or three, one and two and three. That's
also פיגול pigul, even if it's not four. Isn't that obvious? No,
same point. מהו דתימא, mahu detayma, I might have thought אי סלקא
דעתך כל עשיה דעל ראשונו הוא עושה, ee salka datach kol asiya
da'al rishono hu ose, that if we're saying it's על דעת ראשונו,
al da'as rishono, מהדר פיגולי בכל חד וחד למה לי? mehadar pigulei
bechol chad vechad lama li? Why did you repeat it on two?
And why did you repeat it on three? It should have stopped!
And so and therefore that problematizes four. And maybe that we should
say that four דווקא davka isn't פיגול. pigul, קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan that no, we'll still say that it's פיגול. pigul Okay,
anyway it's a difficult read of the ברייתא. Baraisa. You're reading "whether
one, whether two, whether three" to be "one and two and three",
which is exactly what the גמרא Gemara says. והא בין בין קתני.
veha bein bein katani. How can you read it to mean "and"?
The ברייתא Baraisa explicitly says "or this or this". אוקיי קשיא. okay
kashya. That's a that's a little bit of a problem that I'm
reading the "ors" of the ברייתא Baraisa as "ands". Okay. Anyway, bottom
line is that all of the evidence is of course for רבי
מאיר מפגלין בחצי מתיר. Rebbi Meir mifaglin bachatzi matir. For some bizarre
reason ריש לקיש Resh Lakish, wants to read him only when it's
the first one and because of כל העושה על דעת ראשון הוא
עושה. kol haose al da'as rishon hu ose. And now what the
גמרא Gemara is going to do, now that we're sort of done
sort of trying, you know, challenging ריש לקיש Resh Lakish. and giving
whatever weak defenses were given, the גמרא's Gemara going to go back
to obviously what the פשט is. And the גמרא Gemara is going
to assume that according to רבי מאיר מפגלין בחצי מתיר, Rebbi Meir
mifaglin bachatzi matir, so it's really quite fascinating. So we're saying fine,
we're done with that, but let's go back to what we know
is the אמת. emes. Let's go back to מפגלין בחצי מתיר. matir.
אמר מר, amar mar, so now let's look at that ברייתא Baraisa
without having to deal with ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish Okay. אמר מר:
amar mar: רבי מאיר אומר פיגול pigul וחייבין עליו כרת. מכדי, michdi,
כרת לא מחייב עד שיקרבו כל
מתיריו. kares lo mechayev ad sheyikrevu kol matirav. We know that פיגול
pigul you're not חייב until you do all the rest of the
קרבן korban, correctly, right? That's the general principle. Alright? דאמר מר, da'amar
mar, כהרצאת כשר כן הרצאת פסול. kehartza'as kasher ken hartza'as pasul. Like
we said, it
says ירצה, yeratze, that you have to make... the same way you
make a כשר kasher קרבן korban everything is properly, even this פיגול
pigul קרבן korban. for it to be פיגול pigul everything other than
the פיגול pigul has to be proper. Okay. If that's true, why
don't I challenge it this way?
מה הרצאת כשר עד שיקריבו כל מתיריו אף
הרצאת פסול עד שיקריבו כל
מתיריו. ma hartza'as kasher ad sheyakrivu kol matirav af hartza'as pasul ad
sheyakrivu kol matirav. Okay, so normally you have to do everything else
properly. והא, veha, here's the problem says the גמרא, Gemara, כיון דחישב
בפנים פסלה, kevan dechishev bifnim pasla,
so כמאן דלא עביד דמי. keman delo avid dami. Once you had
the thought of פיגול pigul in this stage, let's say at the
כפורת, kaporet, you've invalidated it and the דם dam is now פסול
pasul דם. dam. So now when you're going out and doing it
at the פרוכת paroches, and at this or whatever, you're putting פסול
pasul דם dam on the, you know, on that. So why is
that considered הרצאת כשר? hartza'as kasher? At this stage it's הרצאת פסול.
hartza'as pasul. Now you're going to ask an obvious question which Michael
will ask us in one second. והא כיון דחישב בפנים פסלה כמאן
דלא עביד דמי, veha kevan dechishev bifnim pasla keman delo avid dami,
so the rest should be like you didn't put the blood. So
כי הדר מטי בה... ki hadar mati bah... היכל, Heichal, מיא בעלמא
הוא דקאדי. Mayah be'alma hu dekadi. So when you're doing this stuff
here by the מזבח, mizbeach it's like it's water at this stage,
not blood.
מזי Madi is in מזה? mazeh?
מזה. Mazeh. So why are you, why
is this considered like you did the rest properly? So what's the
obvious question?
I mean, actually, what I was thinking is, if you do, if
you're מפיגול mapigul on this, you're not allowed to go back in
and do it.
All right, don't tell me that. What's the obvious question here? גמרא
Gemara says you don't have, you're not doing the rest properly because
once you had a פיגול pigul thought, the blood is פסול pasul
and everything after that.
Are we still adhering to this that you did another שחיטה?
shechitah, No, no, no, no. Simple, straight case. Okay? Straight case, no
other שחיטה, shechitah, you did the blood here, blood here, da-da-da-da-da, and
the גמרא's Gemara saying מפיגלין בחצי מתיר mapiglin bechatzi matir according to
Rabbi Meir. But the גמרא Gemara says, I don't get it. If
it's מפיגול בחצי מתיר, mapigul bechatzi matir, as soon as you made
it פיגול, pigul how do we say you did the rest properly?
So the obvious question, Michael, you're not on your game. The obvious...
that's teasing you, Michael. The obvious question is that's true by every
פיגול. pigul Okay? When I do שחיטה, shechitah. I make the... and
I have a פיגול pigul thought, the blood's invalid. So how do
you say, "Oh, you have to do the rest properly to make
it פיגול"? pigul. When I get... if I had a פיגול pigul,
thought at שחיטה, shechitah. then the זריקה is מיא בעלמא. mayim be'alma.
It's just at this stage פסול. pasul.
So why would we ask this on the רבי?
So but we're not.
Normal פיגול pigul we're fine. All of a sudden, we understand that
when I'm normally assessing פיגול, pigul. I sort of say, bracketing the
fact that it's פיגול, pigul was the rest done properly? That's how
I frame my question of עד שיקריבו כל מתיריו. ad sheyakrivu kol
matirov.
So why don't I say here, bracketing the fact that it's פיגול,
pigul everything else is done properly? Why all of a sudden now
are you bothered with, oh, you had a פיגול pigul thought and
now it's like it's not really blood and now the whole thing
is פסול? pasul? So this is what bothers רש"י Rashi and תוספות
obviously. And רש"י says the basic point here is that we understand
the idea of bracketing when what you're bracketing is a whole act.
You had פיגול pigul during שחיטה. shechitah Let's bracket the שחיטה. shechitah,
Everything else was done properly, okay? Here, you're not bracketing a whole
act. Remember, this is all one process of blood, okay? So partly
you had a פיגול pigul, thought. So how can we say in
this same process, right? if you had... this is the irony: if
you had a פיגול pigul thought at every single step, like the
חכמים, Chachamim okay? You had a פיגול pigul thought with blood. Bracketing
that, everything else was done properly. Bracketing the stuff that had the
פיגול pigul? done to it, and pretending the פיגול pigul didn't happen,
so bracketing that thing, everything else was done properly. But here, within
one process, okay, what are you going to say? If you because
because you can't see this all as a פיגול pigul. process and
bracket the whole thing, because only part of it was a פיגול
pigul process. So if you're looking at this one act, okay, and
you have to assess the act: was this a פיגול pigul act
or a non-פיגול pigul act? You can't give it one label. If
you could give the whole thing a פיגול pigul act label, then
you could bracket it. But because you can't, the problem is that
from the perspective of this act is both partly פיגול, pigul partly
not, so when we look at this act, we sort of have
to say it's פסול pasul without saying that it's פיגול, pigul. right?
It's פסול pasul because part of it was פיגול, pigul not because
the whole thing is פיגול. pigul So that's what רש"י says. Because
it is within the same act, that's why it bothers us. Because
it's within the same act, we say we can't bracket the פיגול
pigul reality because that's not a label that applies to the whole
act. And since we can't bracket the פיגול pigul reality, we have
to look at this act and say part of an act was
okay and part of it wasn't okay, and therefore, so you didn't
have כל מתיר מתיריו, kol mateir matirav, because you didn't have a
legitimate זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. And if the reason you didn't have
a legitimate זריקת הדם zrikas hadam is because we could call the
whole thing פיגול, pigul we're allowed to bracket that. But if you
can't call the whole thing פיגול, pigul then we just have to
say this is a, you know, a partially good, partially bad act,
and therefore, so you never had a זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam, so
we can't say you had the principle of כל מתיר מתיריו. kol
matir matirav. That's what seems to be bothering the גמרא. Gemara. The
answer's going to be like you don't have to say that. Just
bracket פיגול pigul. even in the middle of an act. Okay? So
let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, משכחת לה בארבע פרים ובארבע שעירים. mishkachas
lah be'arba parim uve'arba se'irim. So רבא Rava first says, because Michael
wanted us to reintroduce the other cows, so Michael basically says, no,
here's how we could bracket it: that you have a cow brought
here, you spill the blood, a cow brought here, a cow brought
here, and so on. And in those types of cases, since everything
is discrete, right? because if you had to spill and brought more,
that allows us even though it's a חצי מתיר, matir it allows
us to see it as a discrete unit and to bracket it,
okay? So if the stuff spilled and I brought a cow here
and it spilled again and I brought a cow here, right? or
whatever, and a cow here, whether you can separate those two or
not is a question. Okay, in that type of a case, and
my פיגול pigul. thought was פיגול בין בראשון בין בשני בין בשלישי.
pigul bein bahrishon bein bashniya bein bashlishis. So my פיגול pigul thought
was during כפורת, or just during פרוכת, or just during this. Okay,
fine, but now I had... a פיגול pigul, thought on a whole
discrete unit and I can bracket it and I can say the
rest was done properly. So if I didn't have the קו, kav,
I look at the whole thing as one unit, right? and I
say I can't bracket it. This unit is partly good partly bad.
But if I have the קו kav and then I pick up
where I left off, that allows me to bracket that as a
discrete unit and say the פיגול pigul? was for this and that
and bracketing this, the rest are separate acts and those were done
properly. Okay, so that's רבא's Rava answer. David, you look like you're
not getting it. No, no, I'm trying. But so are the other
acts then considered valid or are they still? Well, if you hadn't
had the פיגול pigul, they would be valid. So the point is
bracketing the פיגול pigul, because we brought another קו kav and we
were able to pick off and we didn't have to go back,
that means whatever was done there was separate and that and we're
allowed now to continue. And therefore if what was done there was
פיגול pigul and the פיגול pigul label applied to the whole thing,
then we can say okay that was a פיגול pigul, act, bracket
that, the rest of the acts are done properly. But if we
didn't have the קו, kav, okay, then it's one big process and
then that's the גמרא's Gemara problem. It can't part a process can't
both partly be פיגול pigul, and partly not be פיגול. pigul. I
mean it can, but then you don't have the principle of מתיר
כל מתיריו. matir kol matirav. That's what the גמרא's. Gemara But with
a regular קרבן, korban just forgetting this for a minute, like you
know I did the שחיטה wrong, פיגול, pigul, right? Right. I shouldn't
be going no one should be going on with the rest of
it. But you know but they do because no one's talking to
each other or the same כהן just doesn't care. If this is
a sermon, the only way פיגול pigul can happen is if people
don't communicate. You'd expect to stop it right there. Right. You're totally
right. So to the same extent it's like my but you know
but that's just one of the oddities of פיגול. pigul I understand.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara says so that's רבא's Rava answer that
you actually had these extra קוs. kav רבא אמר אפילו תימא בפר
אחד ושעיר אחד לפיגול מרצה. Rava amar afilu teima bepar echad vese'ir
echad lipigul meratzeh. All right so he finally says you don't have
to make this complicated thing.
Since we bracket the פיגול reality to assess כל עד שירצה כל
מתיריו kol ad sheyeratzeh kol matirav by the other parts, you know
when it's a discrete act we bracket the פיגול reality.
So even if it's a piece of a process we bracket the
פיגול reality. So even if it's one long process or whatever and
part of this was פיגול and the part next, we can still
assess is it עד שיקריב כל מתיריו ad sheyakriv kol matirav by
saying bracketing the פיגול, even the פיגול on a piece of this,
the rest of it was done properly. We don't need it to
be discrete in order to bracket it. Okay so basically that difficult
you know that complicated explanation I had to give why all of
a sudden the גמרא's Gemara bothered here and it's not bothered elsewhere
because elsewhere it's discrete and it can be bracketed and here it's
not discrete.
רבא Rava says you don't have to make that distinction and even
though it's not discrete you can bracket it. Okay fine. Now kid's
easy we said totally sort of different point we said there are
43 applications of blood, right? by יום כיפור Yom Kippur there
are ברייתות that mention a different number. So the גמרא Gemara says
ארבעים ושלושה arba'im ushlosha now 43 והתניא ארבעים ושבעה
vehatanya arba'im vesheva we've got a ברייתא baraita that says 47.
הא כמאן דאמר מערבין לקרנות הא
כמאן דאמר אין מערבין לקרנות.
ha keman de'amar me'arvin
lekranot ha
keman de'amar ein me'arvin lekranot. So the question is oh I think
I had it
right sorry I don't know why as I often say last time
I thought I was wrong I was mistaken. Okay so I had
it right the first time four on the corners. So okay so
do you have 43 or 47? So the question here is okay
the reason this is no that's like the that's like the seven
on the top. Okay back to my first mistake. Okay anyway that's
like the professor that comes and says the math professor so he's
writing all these equations on the board and he says and then
from this it trivially follows and then from this it trivially follows
he says no no wait a second wait a second he erases
it he thinks thinks thinks thinks yes it does trivially follow. So
anyway all right so anyway okay so the question here is the
reason here it's 11 and not 22 is because at this stage
this is where you mix the bloods together, okay you have the
פר blood and the שעיר se'ir blood and then you're going to
do not times two because they're mixed together. Okay so the question
is okay do you mix them together before or after the corners?
If you mix them together before the corners you have 11 and
you get 43. Doesn't תורה Torah give you an order? No it
says it just says ולקח מדם הפר ומדם השעיר ונתן על קרנות
המזבח velakach middam hapar umiddam hase'ir venatan al karnot hamizbe'ach I think
it says. So if you say אין מערבין לקרנות ein me'arvin lekranot
so then you do it after the corners, okay and then you
multiply and then you have two applications of the four corners so
then instead of 43 you're going to get 47. All right so
that's the question הא כמאן דאמר מערבין לקרנות הא כמאן דאמר אין
מערבין לקרנות.
ha keman de'amar me'arvin lekranot ha keman
de'amar ein me'arvin lekranot.
והתניא ארבעים ושמונה. vehatanya arba'im ushmonah. Okay לקרנות. l'karnot. It's קרנות, karnot,
right? לקרנות. l'karnot. הא כמאן דאמר מערבין לקרנות ha kamandamar arvin l'karnot
הא כמאן דאמר אין מערבין לקרנות. ha kamandamar ein marvin l'karnot. והתניא
ארבעים ושמונה. ve-tanya arba'im v'shmonah.
Okay so now we can see how you can get up to
forty-seven. How can you get up to forty-eight? There's a ברייתא braita
that says forty-eight. So the גמרא Gemara says הא כמאן דאמר שיריים
מעכבין ha kamandamar shirayim akvin הא כמאן דאמר אין שיריים מעכבין. ha
kamandamar ein shirayim akvin. Ah because we didn't mention one final
part, the spilling of
the blood that you do on the outside altar. I'm sorry, where?
I'm lost here. So he says, when we say this פסוק pasuk
וצא אל המזבח אשר לפני ה' וכפר עליו ולקח מדם הפר ומדם
השעיר ונתן על קרנות המזבח סביב. ve-yatza el ha-mizbe'ach asher lifnei Hashem
ve-kipper alav ve-lakach mi-dam ha-par u-mi-dam ha-sa'ir ve-natan al karnot ha-mizbe'ach saviv.
Yes. And then it says והזה עליו מן הדם באצבעו שבע פעמים.
ve-hizah alav min ha-dam be-etzba'o sheva pe'amim. Right. So the first part
says מדם הפר ומדם השעיר mi-dam ha-par u-mi-dam ha-sa'ir and then it
says מן הדם. min ha-dam. Right? So that's exactly the point. From
here it says מדם הפר ומדם השעיר mi-dam ha-par u-mi-dam ha-sa'ir so
does that mean mixed together or does that mean each one distinct?
And by the top it says מן הדם, min ha-dam, right, which
clearly is that it's now just one collection of blood. So that's
exactly the debate. Okay, do you read that as separate still by
the corners or do you read it as mixed? Thank you for
quoting the פסוק. pasuk. Thank you for proving my point. So anyway,
alright. So anyway the question about forty-eight now is you take the
rest of the blood and you spill it on the outside מזבח.
mizbeach Okay. And remember we actually had a whole thing before about
whether by
the inner חטאות chata'ot does we
said before שיריים shirayim is not מעכב me'akev but we left it
a little vague, like is that really true by יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, is that really true? So it's really a debate whether the
spilling of the שיריים shirayim is מעכב me'akev by the inner חטאת
and if it is that would get you to forty-eight. Okay, מתיבי
meitivei says the גמרא. Gemara. Still though is that our משנה mishnah
says שירי הדם הוא שופך אל יסוד מערבי של מזבח החיצון ואם
לא נתן לא עכב
shirei ha-dam hu shofech el
yesod ma'aravi shel mizbe'ach ha-chitzon ve-im lo natan lo ikev which is
in איזהו מקומן? Ezehhu Mekoman? Right. So you're saying that's debated? Yes.
Okay, so now מתיבי meitivei says the גמרא Gemara again where we're
still now going back to attack ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish. not attack
whatever, challenge ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish Okay and here's another ברייתא. braita.
במה דברים אמורים when is it true, okay, that פיגול on one
act creates פיגול? Now we're dealing with a מנחה. בקמיצה bi-kmitzah when
you do it by the taking of the hand-breath that's like שחיטה,
במתן כלי be-matan kli by putting
it in the vessel that's like קבלה, kabbalah, ובהילוך u-be-hiloch walking, any
one of those is a full act and that פיגול makes פיגול.
אבל when it comes to offering
it up on the מזבח there's
two parts, there's two מתירין. אבל בא להקטרה aval ba le-haktarah
when you're coming to offering it up on the
מזבח נתן את הקומץ במחשבה ואת הלבונה בשתיקה natan et ha-kometz be-machshavah
ve-et ha-levonah be-shtikah if you did the קומץ with a פיגול thought
and the לבונה levonah without or שנתן את הקומץ בשתיקה ואת הלבונה
במחשבה o she-natan et ha-kometz be-shtikah ve-et ha-levonah be-machshavah or the קומץ
was silent and then the לבונה levona was with the פיגול thought,
רבי מאיר אומר פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת וחכמים אומרים אין בו כרת
עד שיפגל בכל המתירין. Rabbi Meir omer pigul ve-chayavin alav karet va-chachamim
omrim ein bo karet ad she-yefagel be-chol ha-matirin. רבי מאיר says even
by one of them it's enough to create פיגול and the חכמים
Chachamim say you need it by both of them. So here it
seems quite explicit that it gave a scenario where first you were
silent, first you didn't have the פיגול thought and then you had
the פיגול thought and רבי מאיר says guess what, that creates פיגול.
קתני מיהא we teach nonetheless את הקומץ בשתיקה ואת הלבונה במחשבה et
ha-kometz be-shtikah ve-et ha-levonah be-machshavah that first the קומץ was silent and
then the לבונה was with the פיגול thought and still even though
it's not first, it's not based on כל העושה על דעת ראשונה
הוא עושה kol ha-oseh al da'at rishonah hu oseh even though it's
in the middle,
that's enough for פיגול for רבי מאיר. ופליג u-palig and רבי מאיר
disagrees with the חכמים. אימא eima so ריש לקיש would tell you
אימא eima no, read the ברייתא braita to me כבר נתן את
הלבונה במחשבה. kvar natan et ha-levonah be-machshavah.
So when it says you did the קומץ in silence and then
the לבונה with a פיגול thought, rather than reading and then you
did the קומץ with a פיגול thought, read it to say and
you had already done the לבונה with a פיגול thought. Okay so
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, חדא דהיינו רישא. chada de-hainu reisha.
If that were true it's just repeating the point it made above.
So first of all why if I even if I would have
forced that words into that it would make it just redundant, so
why so that's obviously not the right reading. ועוד הא תניא ואחר
כך. ve-od ha tanya ve-achar kach. We have another ברייתא braita that
adds the words explicitly that first you did act one with silence
and afterwards, says the words, and afterwards did act two with a
פיגול thought and רבי מאיר says that makes it פיגול. So the
גמרא Gemara ends קשיא. kashya. You're right. That's difficult for ריש לקיש.
I mean I would say it's a lot more than קשיא, kashya,
right? It seems to me that it's clear that all of the
evidence shows that for רבי מאיר מפגלין בחצי מתיר. matir. For some
reason ריש לקיש wants to re-read רבי מאיר and that forces him
to re-read a lot of evidence. Okay. I guess we will end
here or maybe if you want to just because we have a
few more minutes we'd just be able to begin the משנה mishnah
that we'll probably re-read it tomorrow, but let's begin it. ואלו דברים
שאין חייבין עליהם משום פיגול. ve-elu devarim she-ein chayavin aleihem mishum pigul.
Let's say you finally managed to walk through this whole minefield and
I'm just teasing and you finally succeeded in making the קרבן korban
פיגול. Yay. Okay, so now now you're חייב for eating a כזית
of a פיגול קרבן. korban You're חייב כרת. chayav karet. You're not
חייב כרת chayav karet for making it פיגול, you're חייב for eating
it. What part of the קרבן korban, do you have to eat
to make it פיגול? And one so one of the answers is
you have to eat the edible part, edible is not limited I
should say to what's normally edible but first of all it's physically
edible, not the hoofs. But it's also not—it's things that would normally—the
מצוה mitzvah would be to eat them, whether you eat them or
the מזבח eats them. Have you ever heard of a burrito? So
you're going to be חייב for eating the meat; you're going to
be חייב for eating, you're going to be חייב for eating the
entrails, okay, that you're חייב for. Okay, but it does not apply
to the part of the קרבן korban, that is called the מתיר.
matir We've been dealing with the מתיר. matir, So the thing that
is makes the קרבן korban valid, the איסור issur of פיגול, the
דוקא davka the thing through which agency you created פיגול, the איסור
issur of פיגול doesn't apply to that thing itself. Okay, so you
got it? So the blood, even though
we consider blood a type of אכילת מזבח achilas mizbeach and a
פיגול thought about blood is, you know, is considered a thought about
אכילה, achila, right, and makes פיגול, but since the blood is the
thing, the מתיר, matir, the thing that is making the פיגול, okay,
it is not the object
of the פיגול. It is not—if you eat the blood you'd be
חייב כרת chayav kares for eating the blood. Well, that's true. You
could cook it, you could do things to get out of the
כרת. Okay, and similarly the קומץ of the מנחה. Even though it's
exactly the, you know, it's still whatever, the same type of flour
and water as the rest, okay, and even though there's an אכילת
מזבח achilas mizbeach by burning it, since it is the מתיר, פיגול,
the laws of פיגול don't apply to it. I'm sure there's a
sermon in that too. Okay, here you are, you know, you create—it's
like the typhoid Mary, you know, you go ahead, you create all
the problem but it doesn't apply to you, you know, you get
out scot-free. Anyway, ואלו דברים שאין חייבין עליהם משום פיגול. Ve-elu devarim
she-ein chayavin aleihem mishum pigul. הקומץ, so the handbreadth again because it's
the מתיר, okay, והקטורת, ve-haketores, the frankincense, והלבונה, ve-halevona, which—I mean it
should be הלבונה והקטורת. halevona ve-haketores. Anyway, the לבונה is the frankincense
that goes with the מנחה, the קטורת is the קטורת that's burnt
on the inner altar. ומנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח, U-minchas kohanim u-minchas
kohen mashiach, the מנחה of either a סתם, a מנחת נדבה minchas
nedava of a כהן, or a regular obligatory daily מנחה of the
כהן גדול. These are things that are fully burnt, okay. והדם, Ve-hadam,
והנסכים הבאים בפני עצמן, ve-hanesachim ha-ba'im bifnei atzman, and the blood and
the blood which is a מתיר, okay, and והנסכים הבאים בפני עצמן.
ve-hanesachim ha-ba'im bifnei atzman. Now that's a little bit strange because that's
not actually a מתיר, okay, or it sort of could be, which
is if you basically just are מתנדב misnadeiv to bring נסכים, to
bring like, you know, wine on the מזבח, or you have a
מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, you have a, you know, the flour, water
and the wine that comes with a קרבן, korban, and—but you didn't
bring it on the day of the קרבן, korban you brought it
on its own on a later day. So the הלכה is that
you can bring it on its own. Now when you bring it
on its own on a later day, okay, that's בפני עצמו, bifnei
atzmo, then what is the מתיר? What allows that to be put
on the מזבח? You getting me when you just bring it by
itself? Normally, you have something that's put on the מזבח that allows
like that allows the rest to be eaten. That's like our normal
model. But there's some things that are burnt fully on the מזבח
and those are considered to essentially be מתיר עצמן. matir atzman. They're
not the stuff that's left over after the מתיר. So when this
is the wine and the whatever is brought separately without a קרבן
coming with it, that is considered to not be the object to
which the act of מתיר applied, to which, you know, that is
considered to be the thing that it is itself מתיר. It's making—it's
legitimating itself and it's being brought by itself. So then it operates
sort of like the מנחת כהנים and so on. Okay, so that's
דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי מאיר says. וחכמים
אומרים אף הבאים עם הבהמה. Ve-Chachamim omrim af ha-ba'im im ha-behema. And
the חכמים say even when it comes with the even when it
comes with the בהמה, behema, because even since in theory—now this is
a really fascinating point—in theory you could bring it on a different
day, so even though today you're bringing this wine and flour and
oil etc. with your קרבן, and in this scenario, you know, the
קרבן functions as the מתיר for this. What? You bring it a
different day? How much time do you have? What do you mean?
You mean a different day? You do it like a year later?
I don't know. Okay, yeah, אפילו אחרי עשרה ימים. afilu acharei asara
yamim. Anyway, the חכמים say and we'll explore this more in the
גמרא, Gemara, you know, the חכמים say that this is what do
you call—that this is נו, nu, that—that the חכמים say that this
makes this considered to be something that is its own מתיר, since
in theory it could be its own מתיר, and therefore the laws
of פיגול do not apply to it. Okay, so we'll end the
משנה mishnah at this stage and we will pick up what do
you call here tomorrow on Shabbos.